<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<schemalist gettext-domain="gdm">
  <schema id="org.gnome.login-screen" path="/org/gnome/login-screen/">
    <key name="enable-fingerprint-authentication" type="b">
      <default>true</default>
      <summary>
        Whether or not to allow fingerprint readers for login
      </summary>
      <description>
        The login screen can optionally allow users who have enrolled
        their fingerprints to log in using those prints.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="enable-smartcard-authentication" type="b">
      <default>true</default>
      <summary>
        Whether or not to allow smartcard readers for login
      </summary>
      <description>
        The login screen can optionally allow users who have smartcards
        to log in using those smartcards.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="enable-password-authentication" type="b">
      <default>true</default>
      <summary>
        Whether or not to allow passwords for login
      </summary>
      <description>
        The login screen can be configured to disallow password authentication,
        forcing the user to use smartcard or fingerprint authentication.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="logo" type="s">
      <default>''</default>
      <summary>
        Path to small image at top of user list
      </summary>
      <description>
        The login screen can optionally show a small image to provide site
        administrators and distributions a way to display branding.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="fallback-logo" type="s">
      <default>''</default>
      <summary>
        Path to small image at top of user list
      </summary>
      <description>
        The fallback login screen can optionally show a small image to provide
        site administrators and distributions a way to display branding.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="disable-user-list" type="b">
      <default>false</default>
      <summary>
        Avoid showing user list
      </summary>
      <description>
        The login screen normally shows a list of available users to log in
        as. This setting can be toggled to disable showing the user list.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="banner-message-enable" type="b">
      <default>false</default>
      <summary>
        Enable showing the banner message
      </summary>
      <description>
        Set to true to show the banner message text.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="banner-message-text" type="s">
      <default>''</default>
      <summary>
        Banner message text
      </summary>
      <description>
        Text banner message to show in the login window.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="disable-restart-buttons" type="b">
      <default>false</default>
      <summary>
        Disable showing the restart buttons
      </summary>
      <description>
        Set to true to disable showing the restart buttons in the login window.
      </description>
    </key>
    <key name="allowed-failures" type="i">
      <default>3</default>
      <summary>
        Number of allowed authentication failures
      </summary>
      <description>
        The number of times a user is allowed to attempt authentication, before
        giving up and going back to user selection.
      </description>
    </key>
  </schema>
</schemalist>
